בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ט"ו, tes-vav, 15. We
pick up on the very top of י"ד עמוד ב', yud-dalet amud-bet,
the משנה, mishna, and we are continuing with these משניות mishnayot which
are very cryptic and written almost in a different type, in a,
you know, archaic language. One wonders again, I know the scholarship on
it exactly, the assumption being that these משניות mishnayot are very early
משניות. mishnayot. One can appreciate in terms of their more opaqueness here
what an amazing job רבי Rebbe did in editing and organizing the
משנה mishna that most משניות mishnayot in ש"ס Shas don't sound like
this. But here we go with another משנה mishna that is very
terse and cryptic and the גמרא's Gemara going to unpack, which tries
to sort of give some general principles in terms of what is
the liability for damages. So let's take a look, top
of י"ד עמוד ב'. yud-dalet amud-bet. שום כסף שוה כסף בפני בית
דין ועל פי עדים בני חורין בני ברית ונשים בכלל הנזק והניזק
והמזיק בתשלומין. Shum kesef, shaveh kesef, bifnei beit din, ve-al pi edim,
bnei chorin bnei brit, ve-nashim bichlal ha-nezek, ve-hanizak ve-hamazik betashlumin. Well, that's
clear enough. Okay.
It's almost like a little bit of a poem or something. Okay,
and now you have to figure out what it all means. So
let's see, the גמרא Gemara will figure out what it means. Okay.
מאי שום כסף? Mai shum kesef? Let's start with the first one,
an assessment of money. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, שום זה
לא יהא אלא בכסף. shum zeh lo yehei ela bekesef. When you
assess the loss, you should do it in based on the dollar
amount. אמר, Amar, so תנינא להא דתנו רבנן, tanina lada d-tanu rabanan,
we taught in our משנה mishna what was said more explicitly in
a
ברייתא. braita. פרה שהזיקה טלית וטלית שהזיקה פרה, Para she-izika talit, ve-talit
she-izika para, a פרה para and a טלית talit got into a
fight. Who do you think's going to win? So anyway, apparently they
damaged one another. The טלית, talit, the פרה para slipped on the
טלית, talit, it was a type of a בור ברשות הרבים, bor
birshut harabim, the פרה, para, the cow either gored or tore up
or ate the טלית, talit, and they did damage to one another.
תוספות Tosafot figures out exactly where is it that this happened. Now
if the טלית talit you're חייב chayav for that, that would be
in a רשות הרבים. rishut harabim. If the פרה para ate the
טלית talit and it's a type of a שן, shen, that would
have to be ברשות הניזק. birshut hanizak. So maybe it gored the
טלית talit or maybe it was an eating that's not a natural
type of an eating. Anyway, we're not going to worry about that,
but they did damage to one
another. Okay, אין אומרים צא פרה בטלית וטלית בפרה. ein omrim tze
para be-talit ve-talit be-para. Don't just say, hey, you know, we'll just
call the whole thing a swap. Okay? אלא שמנין אותן בדמים. Ela
shamnin otan bidamim. No, you don't just say, well, you know, there
was damage to the טלית, talit, damage to the פרה, para, we'll
just say it's all evened out. No, no, no. You figure out
how much damage to the טלית, talit, how much damage to the
פרה, para, and you figure out the difference and whoever has the
balance of the difference pays the difference. Now this all seems relatively
obvious, like why logically should I have thought of doing anything else?
So תוספות Tosafot says that there's two חידושים chidushim here. חידוש Chidush
number one is, is that if
he sort of sees this not as the same scenario, but different
scenarios. So number one is that the פרה para damaged the טלית.
talit. Okay, so or let's actually start the other way, the טלית,
talit, no, the פרה para damaged, okay, the פרה para damaged the
טלית. talit. So the חידוש chidush here is, wait let me just
check תוספות Tosafot again to remind myself,
right,
so if the פרה para damaged the טלית, talit, you have to
pay for the damage to the טלית. talit. Now if the פרה
para did this, if it was a קרן keren and it was
a תם, tam, let everybody remember what's the הלכה halakha about a
קרן תם? keren tam? You pay half the value and up to
what?
Up to the value of the actual goring animal itself. Now we
are going to see in a little bit that there's going to
be a debate between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael whether when you whether the idea that that money gets paid
out of the body of the animal itself. It's not just limited
to the value of the animal, but does it actually get paid
out of the body of the animal itself? Do you become a
part owner in the cow? And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that
as soon as your cow gores my cow, I automatically become a
part owner in your cow. It's not just you owe me money.
I now own a percentage of your cow automatically.
Yes, like a gneiva issue.
Well,
you gored something you own it, you're a type of, no,
no, no, it's the opposite. You are the מזיק, mazik, your animal
gored, let's even say you think gored my cow, your ox gored
my sheep for $100. I now own $100 of your ox. It's
not gneiva, it's the opposite. You did the bad thing to me
and now I own something of yours. Okay, so that's רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva idea. רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva idea is that you automatically
own a piece of the goring ox, it's called יוחלט השור. yuchlaf
hashor. So תוספות Tosafot says that that's what we're saying is not
true. This משנה mishna is teaching against רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. It's
saying you don't say צא פרה בטלית tze para be-talit means you
don't just get an ownership of the cow. The guy owes you
the money. It's limited to the value of the cow, but it
does not translate into a direct ownership of the cow. Okay, so
that's one part of the חידוש chidush here, that even in a
case of a goring ox, not like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you
pay. Money, it does not become an ownership in the cow. What
about the other חידוש? chiddush? The other חידוש chiddush is that my
טלית talis caused your ox to slip. You don't get an ownership
of the טלית. talis. Now why is that a חידוש? chiddush? Right?
Of course you don't get an ownership of the טלית. talis. So
I mean I owe you the money, it's a בור. bor. So
תוספות Tosfos says no, the חידוש chiddush here is the following, is
let me again just double check תוספות. Tosfos. Oh, the חידוש chiddush
is the following, is that yes, the owner of the טלית talis
has to pay you for your $100 of damage for your ox.
But we're going to see in a minute, let's say the owner
died and he has then you could have to collect from the
orphans, the heirs. You can only collect from things you have liens
on. You can't and if he has no landed property, you're out
your damages. Right?
It's only liens and if he's not alive, then you're out. So
here you might want to say look, maybe I should say the
following, maybe I should say that at least I have rights to
the actual טלית talis itself that did the damage. So even though
he has no land property and I have no liens and I
can't collect from the orphans, come on, at least I should be
able to seize the actual טלית talis that did the damage itself.
And the answer is no, you don't do that either, it's just
an amount of money that is owed to you. So the חידוש
chiddush is in both ways. The bigger חידוש chiddush is if the
ox is a goring ox, you don't say like רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva you own the ox. No, the owner of the ox owes
you money, you don't own the ox. But in the flip case
as
well, if the טלית talis is a בור bor and it slips
on the טלית, talis, you have no rights to the טלית. talis.
Even if it means you're going to be out money because the
guy is dead and he didn't leave any land, but you all
the debt here what you owe is in terms of cash, not
in terms of the damaging objects. Yes, Jonathan. Does the לשון lashon
really support that?
Isn't it that it's in something an assessment of money and is
paid with something that has value of money? It doesn't mean you
actually pay with money.
Right,
what we're going to get to the next part of the שוה
כסף shaveh kessef or the value of money. But the point here,
you're right, you don't have to pay cash, but the point is
is that you owe what you owe is a dollar amount. How
you pay it is a different question. But the point is as
opposed to saying, no, it excludes the idea of your ox gored
me, I owe your ox, I own your ox. No, no, you
don't own my ox, you owe me money.
Your ox gored me to the damage of $100 and as you
say...
No, but the way we phrase it is your liability is defined
as you owe me $100. Now, maybe I can collect from certain
types of property, maybe you can pay me certain types of property,
but it is defined as the amount of money you owe me
as opposed to translating immediately into ownership of your ox, ownership of
my טלית. talis. No, but that's a different concept, meaning to say
you owe money and what's the type you pay with is consistent
with the concept of I owe money. To say I owe money
and therefore you're an automatic partner in some of my property is
a completely different idea. So that seems to be what the גמרא'ס
Gemara's interpreting the משנה. Mishna. Yes?
It sounds like this is anything we didn't know already anyway. I
mean we never thought that you would at least...
Well, first of all, there's a debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
רבי ישמעאל, Rebbe Ishmael, so this משנה'ס Mishna's coming down on one
side of it. Anyway, I can't worry too much about that. It's
a very cryptic משנה, Mishna, okay? So we're trying to give some
reasonable read of it. שוה כסף. Shaveh kessef. Now, you pay with
money equivalent. Now, that should would have seemed to be like the
idea we said before that you can even pay with what I
call paper clips, with סובין, subin, okay? Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with this, however. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. The גמרא Gemara
interestingly gives a completely different read of it. שוה כסף מלמד שאין
בית דין נזקקין אלא לנכסים שיש להם אחריות. shaveh kessef melamed she'ein
Beis Din nizkakin ela l'nechasim sheyeish lahem achrayus. So we have a
ברייתא braisa that interprets this. It's again, by the way, it's fascinating,
isn't it? That you have a later Tannaitic source interpreting an earlier
cryptic Tannaitic source. Right? And that you have sometimes even I've pointed
this out before, sometimes even within a משנה, Mishna, you have an
earlier layer of a משנה Mishna that's being elaborated and explained and
given parameters by the later תנאים Tannaim that are mentioned in the
משנה. Mishna. Here you have a ברייתא braisa that is explaining what
clearly was this very early cryptic Tannaitic source about what the payment
was. Okay.
Do we always assume that ברייתות braisos are later?
No, but it's the framing: שוה כסף מלמד שאין בית דין נזקקין.
shaveh kessef melamed she'ein Beis Din nizkakin. The ברייתא braisa is explicitly
commenting on what that phrase means. It's not just teaching a הלכה.
halacha. What does שוה כסף shaveh kessef mean? מלמד שאין בית דין
נזקקין אלא לנכסים שיש להם אחריות. melamed she'ein Beis Din nizkakin ela
l'nechasim sheyeish lahem achrayus. בית דין Beis Din only will sort of
deal with, take, seize property when it's dealing with property that has
liens, meaning land. So interesting, שוה כסף shaveh kessef here means land.
It never meant land before. And anyway, why is that true? If
the מזיק mazik is around, I should be able to collect from
whatever property he has. Okay. אבל אם קדם ניזק ותפס מטלטלין בית
דין גובין לו מהן. aval im kodem nizak v'safas metaltelin Beis Din
govin lo mehen. So בית דין Beis Din will only seize land...
but if the ניזק nezek grabs a chattel from the מזיק mazik
without בית דין beis din actually directly seizing it, then the בית
דין beis din will allow the ניזק nezek to keep the chattel
that he has seized. So this is bizarre. A, why does שוה
כסף shoveh kesef mean land? But B, why should the בית דין
beis din be limited to taking land? Right, normally the land issue
is if the מזיק mazik isn't around, it's his heirs or it's
his people that bought property from him, but if the מזיק mazik
is around, why should the בית דין beis din be limited? So
let's take a look at what the גמרא gemara says. גמרא's Gemara
going to work through both of these. Okay, אמר מר, amar mar,
let's go and unpack this. ובשוה כסף מלמד שאין בית דין נזקקין
אלא לנכסים שיש להם אחריות. uv'shoveh kesef melamed she-ein beis din nizkakim
ela lenekhasim she-yesh lahem achrayus. מאי משמע? mai mashma? Since when does
land mean— שוה כסף shoveh kesef mean land? אמר רבה בר עולא:
amar Rabba bar Ulla: דבר השוה ככסף. davar ha-shaveh ke-kesef. Something that
is worth, you know, as much money in the world, has no
fixed price to it. Okay, and what is it, mind you? דבר
שאין לו אונאה. davar she-ein lo ona'ah. It would be land, 'cause
land there's no overcharging for land because land, you know, there's no
way of setting a fixed market price for it. I mean, it's
also just in a formal way excluded from the פרשה parsha of
אונאה. ona'ah. And therefore it's called שוה כסף shoveh kesef because it
like can be worth an exorbitant amount.
We spoke about this a few days
ago.
We spoke about specific
categories for land.
Or there's fixed categories at least. Right, it's עידית, idit, whatever. Right,
so here it's I guess a difference between a fixed price and
a type of a category. Anyway, it's a hard read as the
גמרא's gemara going to say. עבדים ושטרות נמי אין להם אונאה? avadim
u-shtaros nami ein lahem ona'ah? There's also no prohibition of overcharging by
slaves and, you know, documents of
debt. אלא אמר רבה בר עולא: ela amar Rabba bar Ulla: דבר
הנקנה בכסף. davar ha-nikneh be-kesef. Okay, שוה כסף shoveh kesef means a
type of property that is acquired with money as opposed to משיכה
meshikhah and הגבהה. hagbah. So land is acquired with money. גמרא Gemara
says עבדים ושטרות נמי נקנים בכסף? avadim u-shtaros nami niknim be-kesef? Slaves
and שטרות shtaros are also acquired with money. Now רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot say it's not so clear where שטרות shtaros are acquired
with money. שטרות shtaros here does not mean like you're buying a
manuscript of of you know of the first folio of Shakespeare. שטרות
shtaros here means it's an IOU document, so you're transferring the debt.
So that really doesn't work with money. There's other ways in which
you transfer debt. Anyway, doesn't matter. At least עבדים avadim are acquired
with money. So to what degree does שוה כסף shoveh kesef just
mean land? So אלא אמר רב אשי: ela amar Rav Ashi: no,
שוה כסף ולא כסף. shoveh kesef ve-lo kesef. It means something that's
like money but not really money. והני כלהו כסף נינהו. ve-hani kulu
kesef ninhu. And all chattel is considered to be like money, like
cash. It goes back to the גמרא's gemara point earlier, right? That
the idea of מיטב meitav going back, you know, Dov's reference to
the earlier גמרא, gemara, when you pay land you have to pay
the best quality, but when you pay chattel you can pay even
like the גמרא gemara says סובין, subin, you know, what I call
paperclips, you can pay junk. Okay, because the גמרא gemara assumes that
stuff that you can move around can be more easily liquidated and
transferred into money than land can. So everything that's chattel is considered
to be כסף. kesef. The thing that's like money is land. Okay,
again, that's not normally how we use the term. שוה כסף shoveh
kesef actually we most classically use for chattel that isn't cash. Okay,
but for some bizarre reason the גמרא gemara or the גמרא's gemara
explaining the ברייתא, braisa, the ברייתא braisa for some bizarre reason reads
שוה כסף shoveh kesef to refer to land. The easiest read of
the משנה mishnah by the way is not like the ברייתא. braisa.
שוה כסף shoveh kesef means what we've been saying all along. You
don't have to pay in cash, you can pay in any type
of chattel, right, even סובין. subin. But the ברייתא braisa reads it
as land. Okay, so somehow it means land. Now that it means
land, we have to explain why this הלכה halacha makes sense. Okay,
רמי רב בר יהודה בר חיננא לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. Rami
Rav bar Yehuda bar Chinana le-Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua. תניא שוה
כסף מלמד שאין בית דין נזקקין אלא לנכסים שיש להם אחריות. tanya
shoveh kesef melamed she-ein beis din nizkakim ela lenekhasim she-yesh lahem achrayus.
So this ברייתא braisa says that you can only seize land in
payment of a ניזק, nezek, damages. והתניא? ve-hatanya? But the ברייתא braisa
that we've been dealing with for the beginning of the פרק perek
teaches
ישיב—you yashiv should return the money, לרבות שוה
כסף—anything lerabbos shoveh kesef of equivalent, ואפילו סובין—even va'afilu subin bran! So
the גמרא gemara says no, הכא ביתמי עסקינן. hakha be-yasmei askinan.
Alright, you're right. When we're talking about that you can only— בית
דין beis din will only seize property, it means that the מזיק
mazik isn't alive anymore. If the מזיק mazik is alive, he can
pay with anything and בית דין beis din presumably could seize whatever
they could seize. But if the מזיק mazik isn't alive, then they
have to get from his property that has liens on it. So
they'll go to the heirs, the heirs are not directly obligated in
their father's debt, it's only stuff they inherited from the estate and
not only stuff they inherited from the estate, only land that they
inherited from the estate. And therefore when the בית דין beis din
is dealing with heirs, with orphans, that's when they can only get
land. It has to be land with lit- liens?
Well, it automatically has liens.
If you cause damage to my property, I automatically get liens on
your land. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says ביתמי. be-yasmei. If it's
orphans, אימא סיפא: eima seifa: אם קדם ניזק ותפס מטלטלין בית דין
גובין ליה מהם. im kodem nezek vetafas metaltelin beis din govin lei
mei-hem. So I went ahead, somebody damaged me, he died, he left
orphans, he doesn't have any land, so I'm just going to sneak
into his house one day and steal his VCR or something. Okay,
I know people don't have VCRs anymore, I'm sorry. Okay, I'm going
to steal his iPad, okay, I'm going to— okay so anyway, so
then בית דין beis din will let me keep it. So now
why is that? True. I didn't have a lien on it. The
guy himself is dead. Why do I have rights to the- to
the guy's iPad? Whether it's the orphans' or the father's, I still
don't have a right to it. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי
בייתמי אמאי בית דין גבו ליה מהם? Ei beyasmei amai Beis Din
gavu lei mehem?
So why does בית דין Beis Din let me keep it just
because I grabbed it? If it's orphans. So כדרבה אמר רב נחמן
שתפס מחיים. Kedrabbah amar Rav Nachman shetafas mechayim.
Ah, because I saw the guy was about to die, so what
I did was, and I saw he didn't have any land, so-
so I went to pay him a call at the hospital and
while nobody was looking, I took his iPad. Alright? Or I took
his laptop computer. And now I grabbed it while he was alive.
So normally that wouldn't be acceptable. Like, why can I seize property
in a debt that's owed to me before I've gone through the
normal channels of going through a בית דין Beis Din or having
בית דין Beis Din be the one to make sure the guy
pays. But at the end of the day, now he dies and
I have property that I took while he was alive, and when
he was alive, he directly owed me the money. So therefore, we're
willing to see that now as payment for the money he owed
me, even though I should have gone through more proper channels. Okay?
But I took it when he was alive and when he directly
owed me the money. הכי נמי שתפס מחיים. Hachi nami shetafas mechayim.
So the same way they said- they say that over there, we'll
say that here. Yes?
So is this then an example for- for example of עביד איניש
דינא לנפשיה? avid inish dina l'nafshei?
So that's a good question. I'm actually going to get to a
real interesting עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafshei at the
bottom of כ''ז ע''ב Kaf Zayin Amud Beis if we get there.
But to some degree this might, yes. I mean, because either he-
I mean, I don't need to go to בית דין, Beis Din,
he can pay me for the debt without בית דין Beis Din
having to seize it, right? I mean, he'd be smart to get
witnesses to show that he paid me for the debt so I
didn't try to go ahead and sue him in בית דין Beis
Din later. But for me to go and seize his property, yes,
that is like a type of a classic עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה.
avid inish dina l'nafshei. We'll see that later on. Okay? So that's
a good point. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says: so that's
שום כסף shum kesef and שווה כסף shaveh kesef where שום כסף
shum kesef was as Michael said before, not so clear what חידוש
chiddush it was. שווה כסף Shaveh kesef or- is
being given a read by a ברייתא Beraisa which is very strange.
We would have just said it meant you can pay any type
of chattel. And now the next part: בפני בית דין. bifnei Beis
Din. In the presence of a court. פרט למוכר נכסיו ואחר כך
הלך לבית דין. Prat lemocher nechasav ve'achar kach halach leBeis Din.
So, this is- we're getting back to the whole lien idea. This
would mean that if I went ahead and sold all my property
and only then you took me to court, that I would sort
of say, well, like, tough luck. Like, I didn't- you know, you
have no- I- I mean I sold all my property and then
I spent all the money. So you take me to court and
now I'm a pauper and you're out. Okay? So you have to
catch me in court before I sell my property. So the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, why are you out? Why don't you, if-
if some of the property I sold was land, you should be
able to go and to collect that land. You have a lien
on it. So שמע מינה shma mina are we supposed to infer
from this that לוה ומכר נכסיו ואחר כך בא לבית דין אין
בית דין גובין מהם? loveh umachar nechasav ve'achar kach ba leBeis Din
ein Beis Din govin mehem?
That if you- let's say it was another case, it wasn't נזק.
nezek. Let's say I borrowed money from you, and then I sold
all my property including my land and then I wasted all my
money, gambled it all away, and you took me to בית דין.
Beis Din. You wouldn't be out. You'd be able to go and
collect based on the lien. You don't need בית דין, Beis Din,
the liens get created- the point of this is that the liens
get created automatically. As soon as you damage me, I have liens
on your property. As soon as you borrow money from me, I
have liens on your property. בית דין Beis Din does not create
the lien. בית דין Beis Din can help me in exercising the
lien, but they don't create it. So even if after I borrowed
money I sold away all my property or after I damaged you
I sold it all away, that- and only then we went to
בית דין, Beis Din, that doesn't mean you don't have those liens.
בית דין Beis Din will go help you collect the land that
I sold away. So the גמרא Gemara says what logic is this
to say that you should not be able to collect the lien
just because I did it all before we got to בית דין?
Beis Din? So the גמרא Gemara says
fine. אלא פרט לבית דין הדיוטות. Ella prat leBeis Din hedyotos. בפני
בית דין Bifnei Beis Din means that it has to be a
בית דין Beis Din of a real בית דין, Beis Din, a
בית דין Beis Din of- that has סמיכה. smicha. The סמיכה smicha
is not what we talk today about סמיכה, smicha, it means a
type of a סמיכה smicha that goes back to משה רבינו Moshe
Rabbeinu which empowers people to deal with capital crimes and with קנסות.
knasot. And it cannot be a בית דין Beis Din that's empowered
of commoners, meaning empowered only to deal with דיני ממונות. dinei mammonot.
Now the question is why not? We are dealing with דיני ממונות.
dinei mammonot. Because there are some things here that are קנס. knas.
For example, we're going to get to it, but the big question
about paying half by the goring ox, that might be considered a
קנס. knas. There might be other types of personal injury elements of
that that are considered a קנס. knas. So one of the things
that this is implying is that there are times when you need
a full-fledged בית דין, Beis Din, a בית דין Beis Din of-
of- with סמיכה smicha not a בית דין Beis Din of הדיוטות.
hedyotos. Okay? על פי עדים. Al pi eidim. And through witnesses. פרט.
Prat. Now why do you say witnesses? Of course everything needs a
בית דין, Beis Din, everything needs witnesses. What's the חידוש chiddush here?
So the חידוש chiddush is: פרט למודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים
שהוא פטור. Prat lemodeh beknas ve'achar kach bau eidim shehu patur. Again
we're assuming we'll be dealing with a case of a קנס. knas.
Let's say a case of a goring ox or certain cases of
personal injury. And therefore in those cases of a קנס knas the
same way you need a בית דין Beis Din that has סמיכה.
smicha. You need to have witnesses and even my own self-admission cannot
make me obligated in a fine. This is the important difference between
a fine, a קנס, knas, and ממון. mammon. A fine is a
punishment sort of done through money. But conceptually it is the same
as lashes, right? You know, lashes is a punishment done on my
body, and fine is a punishment done to my wallet. Okay, but
it's basically a type of a punishment. So that punishment in order
for the court to be able to impose a punishment on you,
A, they need a certain degree of authority. They need to have
this סמיכה, semicha, they can't be הדיוטות. hedyotos. They have to more
of like represent divine authority, that's the idea of סמיכה: semicha: עד
האלהים יבא דבר שניהם. ad ha'elohim yavo devar shneihem. So you know,
to sort of impose punishment on people they have to have that
type of authority. Number one, I mean, that's always a question like
political philosophers ask like you know what gives the state the right
to you know use force against its citizens, right? What's sort of
the philosophical underpinning? You know, in הלכה halacha it's obviously it's because
they represent God, they're אלהים. elohim. Okay, so they need that authority,
that סמיכה, semicha, to impose a punishment. Also though, punishments need objective
testimony that the person is deserving of punishment. And if you had
to admit it
yourself, אין אדם משים עצמו רשע. ein adam meisim atzmo rasha. It's
sort of like taking the idea of the fifth amendment, taking the
fifth amendment one step further. The fifth amendment gives you a right
to not self-incriminate. But if you went ahead and self-incriminated, you're stuck
with that, right? הלכה halacha says even if you tried to self-incriminate
we ignore what you said, okay, when it comes to when not
when it comes to civil liability, but when it comes to criminal
or imposing of punishment. It needs to be objective. So if we
are talking here to include cases of קנס, knas, the same way
you need a בית דין beis din of סמיכה, semicha, you need
עדים eidim only and your own self-admission will not be able to
impose a קנס. knas. Now not only can it not impose a
קנס, knas, there's even going to be opinions later on, which the
גמרא gemara references here, that if later witnesses come, because you admitted
it first, you don't have to pay the קנס knas even if
witnesses come later. Now that doesn't apply by lashes. By lashes you'd
have to get the punishment. Okay, but by at least monetary fines
if you admitted it on your own, and that's sort of seen
presumably what that's based on is seeing that the purpose of a
monetary fine might be primarily to make to to sort of, you
know, compel you to come forward and to admit. So therefore if
you go ahead and sort of admit on your own and you
didn't need the witnesses, right then there's maybe no longer any fine,
but that's complicated because some fines like don't seem to be that's
what it's about. The reason when your ox gores me you pay
half damages, it's not just to get you to confess up, right
presumably I'm supposed to try to get some type of compensation even
if technically you're
exempt. Anyway, there is this idea which we'll explore
later, that is debated, but there is an opinion that if you
admit to a fine and witnesses come later, you're completely off the
hook. Of course so the best thing to do is if you
incurred a fine just run to court and admit it. Okay, so
anyway that's what we're saying it's we're talking about. פרט למודה בקנס
ואחר כך באו עדים prat l'modeh b'knas v'achar kach ba'u eidim to
exclude a case of admitting to a fine and then witnesses come
שפטור, shehu patur, that you're exempt. It has to be completely based
on witnesses. הא ניחא למאן דאמר מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים
פטור. ha nicha l'man d'amar modeh b'knas v'achar kach ba'u eidim patur.
That's good if that's the opinion that we take. אלא למאן דאמר
מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים חייב, ela l'man d'amar modeh b'knas
v'achar kach ba'u eidim chayav, but according to the one that says
if witnesses come later you're חייב, chayav, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
l'meimar? What can you say? And presumably it would have been too
obvious just to say that you can't that you can't
self-incriminate. So סיפא איצטריכא ליה. seifa itztricha lei. No, what you need
עדים eidim for is to סיפא איצטריכא ליה, seifa itztricha lei, for
the end of the phrase of עדים. eidim. עדים eidim is obvious.
But it ends by saying עדים בני חורין ובני ברית. eidim bnei
chorin uvnei vrit. Who make legitimate valid witnesses?
Valid witnesses have to be free people who are of the covenant.
בני חורין bnei chorin למעוטי עבדים, l'mautei avadim, free people to exclude
slaves, those are not valid witnesses. Meaning non-Jewish slaves, even though they're
partly obligated in the מצוות. mitzvos. ובני ברית, uvnei vrit, of the
covenant, למעוטי עובדי כוכבים, l'mautei ovdei kochavim, to exclude non-Jews. Both of
those are not valid witnesses. וצריכא, utzricha, you need both. Now you
might have thought that once you exclude slaves who are closer because
they're obligated in מצוות, mitzvos, certainly you would exclude non-Jews. But not
necessarily. דאי אשמעינן עבד, de'i ashmanan eved, if you just excluded slaves
from being witnesses, משום דאין לו יחוס, mishum de'ein lo yichus, he's
doesn't he's not considered to have family relationships. Okay, הלכה halacha doesn't
recognize his family
relationships, basically he means he's on a fundamentally lower status of society,
okay, and therefore you would think of course he can't testify. Like,
you know, he's seen in a very different type of a societal
status. אבל נכרי דיש לו יחוס, aval nochri d'yesh lo yichus, non-Jews,
it happens they're not Jews, but obviously, you know, their family relationships
are recognized and he's considered to be like of equal standing in
society, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe he wouldn't be
excluded. ואי אשמעינן נכרי... ve'i ashmanan nochri... He might be of an
equal societal status, but halachically he's more distant from you, he's completely
not obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. אבל עבד דשייך במצוות, aval eved d'shayach
b'mitzvot, and an עבד eved who's has obligation in מצוות, mitzvot, אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe he shouldn't be excluded from being a slave,
from being an עד. ed. צריכא, tsricha, you need to tell me
both. Interestingly, it doesn't tell me how we know they're excluded. It
just tells me why the ברייתא braita is teaching it. Okay, but
anyway, fine. So that's what we have. It has to be in
front of a בית דין, beis din, it has to be in
front of כשר kosher witnesses. Some of this might be pretty obvious,
but anyway, that's certainly the פשט pshat of the ברייתא. braita. לפני
בית דין, לפני עדים, בני חורין, בני ברית. lifnei beis din, lifnei
edim, bnei chorin, bnei bris. It's pretty clear what it means. Now
we're going to get to the end of the ברייתא braita that
speaks about women and מזיק mazik and ניזק nizak and תשלומין. tashlumin.
Yes, Michael?
Even the end of the משנה mishna was נשים בכלל הנזק, nashim
bekhlal hanezek, but this qualification for עדים, edim, it just says בני
חורין ובני ברית. bnei chorin u'vnei bris. Doesn't exclude women. Right, I
know. Maybe it, you know, it
could be that it's just taken for granted like, you know. Of
course. I mean, right. I mean, you know, I don't know, but
you're right. It is funny. It is funny that right, that women
get mentioned in the end and here what's
excluding who's a כשר kosher witness, it doesn't mention women. Yes. And
women are obviously excluded.
Yeah, and women are excluded. Yeah. What about בני ברית bnei bris
also, what about בני נח bnei noach that מקבל על עצמו שבע?
mekabel al atzmo sheva?
Yeah, that's also like בני ברית bnei bris specifically is, I mean
specifically בני ברית bnei bris although בני ברית bnei bris can include
עבדים, avadim, but it specifically excludes anybody that's more distant in מצוות.
mitzvot. So yeah, בני נח bnei noach would not be relevant, would
be
excluded. Okay, so I was going to say in terms of the
women issue, right, in medieval אשכנז Ashkenaz in the times, you know,
where A, women were just more active in society and they were
involved in business and so on, which leads to a lot of
interesting פסקים, psakim, comes up in the ראשונים, rishonim, they raise interesting
questions about ייחוד yichud and other types of questions since women are
out there doing business and meeting people, etc. Anyway, so one question
also comes up about accepting women's testimony in דיני ממונות dinei mamonos
cases. And effectively, in medieval אשכנז, Ashkenaz, they wound up accepting women's
testimony by just framing it as it's not technical עדות. edus. It's
like circumstantial evidence. בירור דבר. birur davar. Yeah, בירור דבר. birur davar.
If somebody says it, you know, there's a good likelihood that it's
true, right? And you look at the other circumstances. But you know,
it doesn't have formal laws of עדות, edus, but in practice they
wound up accepting, you know, women's testimony in court, but by framing
it as something not as formal עדות. edus. It happened also in
the beginning of, you know, the State of Israel when people were
trying to figure out how could we make a state that runs
according to הלכה halacha and dealt with issues about testimony of women
and non-Jews and so on. And so they basically, you know, saying,
okay, fine, we'll accept it all, we just won't call it עדות.
edus. What? What? I mean, now, no, now they have two parallel
systems. They have the בתי דין batei din and the בתי משפט.
batei mishpat. I don't know what happens in the בתי דין batei
din whether they, how they deal with women's testimony. I really don't.
You know, if somebody actually took a civil case to a בית
דין beis din in Israel right now. I don't know how they
deal with it. I don't know how they do with the BDA,
right? If somebody, you know, woman says, okay, you know. Yeah, I
imagine if somebody took a case right now to the בית דין
beis din of America, you know, some civil case, they agreed to
go to the BDA, I assume they would accept a women's testimony,
right? They would probably follow the, you know, like whatever, the model
of medieval אשכנז, Ashkenaz, which is, okay, technically it's not עדות. edus.
Technically, what do we do עדות edus by now? Do we do
דרישה וחקירה? drisha vechakira? You know, do we do עדים זוממים? edim
zomemim? Like how much do we do formal עדות edus nowadays anyway?
All right, moving on. והנשים בכלל הנזק. v'hanashim bekhlal hanezek. Women are
included in damages. What does this mean? What, in property issues? Yeah,
in property issues, not criminal. But nobody deals with criminal nowadays, you
know what I mean? Okay. והנשים בכלל הנזק. v'hanashim bekhlal hanezek. מנא
הני מילי? mena hani mili? Where is this from? אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל,
vechen tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, אמר קרא. amar kra. The פסוק pasuk
is, איש או אשה כי יעשו מכל חטאת האדם. ish o isha
ki ya'asu mikol chatos ha'adam. If a man or woman does any
of the sins, and then, you know, and then they bring a
קרבן korban because they do it בשוגג. b'shogeg. השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש
לכל עונשים שבתורה. hishvah hakatuv isha l'ish l'chol onashim shebatorah. Any types
of punishments, and this is interesting, punishments here means בשוגג b'shogeg and
mean קרבנות, korbanot, but presumably it also means punishments for מזיד. meizid.
Any types of punishments for transgressions, men and women are equal, apply
equally. Now תוספות Tosfos says the reason it has to say this
is because basically the whole תורה Torah is written בלשון זכר. b'lashon
zachar. The whole תוספות Tosfos is written, the whole תורה Torah is
written בלשון זכר.
b'lashon zachar. The whole תורה Torah is written in the male gender,
right?
It says, right, לא תרצח, lo tirtzach, right? Every, you know, everything
is written in the male. It's talking, so but nevertheless, like standard
English, we write, we presume if he, if he, if he, which
doesn't mean that we're intending to exclude women. Wouldn't it be לא
תרצחי? lo tirtzachi? No, that would be second person. לא תרצח lo
tirtzach is third. I'm making a joke, forget it, sorry. Okay, anyway,
no, I have the grammar right, don't I? How would you say
you shall not commit? You, you would be second person. You, second
person, shall not commit murder is לא תרצחי, lo tirtzachi, right? Okay,
fine. Anyway, okay. I never forget that much of my grammar. Anyway,
okay. Okay. Anyway, so, so, so, but basically the whole תורה Torah,
*Torah* is written in the male gender, the same way like most,
you know, most of everything out, now people are being more trying
to be more careful, you know, in that when they sort of
when they write things and they say, you know, if someone blah
blah blah, then if she, you know, just dropping in she more
frequently, and you know, so that it's not the presumed male actor.
Somebody actually told me that in Israel, you know, you know, basically
all the laws are formulated, you know, again, I'm sure in America
too, they say the
standard gendered formulation is in the masculine,
but that they actually found that there's some principle somewhere,
like in one of the,
you know, in Israeli law, that any law that's written in the
masculine is presumed to apply to the feminine or the feminine to
the masculine unless explicitly stated otherwise. So then this person who was
getting like certain laws trying to get certain laws passed by the
כנסת *Knesset*, just wrote everything in the feminine. So to, you know,
and says it all applies equally. Anyway, so that's what we're dealing
with is that the תורה Torah, *Torah* is all written in the
masculine. How do we assume by default it applies to women as
well? Okay, so therefore this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that says איש ish,
או אשה *ish o isha*, so when it's anything relating to punishments,
since one פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* says איש ish... או אשה *ish o
isha*, השוה הכתוב כל חטאות האדם *hishva hakatuv kol chatot ha-adam*, we
assume השוה הכתוב איש לאשה לכל עונשים onashim שבתורה *hishva hakatuv ish
l'isha l'chol onashim she-ba-Torah*. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא *D'vei Rabbi Yishmael tana*
השוה לקרבנות *hishva l'korbanot*, which is it is, but because it's כל
*kol* we're applying it more broadly. דבי רבי אלעזר תנא *D'vei Rabbi
Elazar tana* ואלה המשפטים אשר תשים לפניהם asher tasim lifneihem. *v'eileh ha-mishpatim
asher tasim lifneihem*, you shall put before them, and before them is
sort of plural and not specifically masculine. So therefore השוה הכתוב איש
לאשה לכל דינים שבתורה *hishva hakatuv ish l'isha l'chol dinim she-ba-Torah*. Any
civil law in the תורה Torah, *Torah* is assumed to apply equally
to men and women. דבי חזקיה ורבי יוסי הגלילי תנא *D'vei Chizkiyah
v'Rabbi Yose Ha-Gelili tana* אמר קרא *amar krah* ונגח איש או אשה
*v'nigach ish o isha*, an ox gores and kills a man or
woman, השוה הכתוב איש לאשה לכל מיתות שבתורה *hishva hakatuv ish l'isha
l'chol mitot she-ba-Torah*. If they are not the subject as it were
but the object, they're not the person who did the sin or
the person who is a litigant in a court case, they are
the injured party, they are the person that was gored by an
ox or that was murdered by someone, so as an injured party
men and women are treated equally. Okay וצריכי *v'tzrichi*, or and you
need all three. דאי אשמעינן קמייתא *di-ashmi-ein kama-isa*, if you had just
said the first one, התם הוא דחס רחמנא rachamana. עלה *hasam hu
d'chas rachmana ala*, there when the תורה torah *Torah* says that women
bring קרבנות korbanot? *korbanot*, the תורה *Torah* had רחמנא *rachmana* on her,
כי היכי דתהוי לה כפרה kapara. *ki-heichi di-tehavi lah kapara* that she
should have an atonement. So it says okay fine, when they do
sins they can bring קרבנות *korbanot*.
אבל דינים *aval dinim*, but when it comes to civil law, that
a woman could be
an equal litigant in civil law and it applies equally to her,
איש דבר משא ומתן *ish de-bar masa u-matan* that he is the
type of person that goes out into the world and does business,
in yes the laws apply to him. אשה לא *isha lo*, but
maybe they don't apply to a woman since the woman's supposed to
be in the home would be the presumption and therefore she would
not be included by civil law. Now what would that mean? She
could damage people and not have to pay, she could borrow money
and not have to pay back? I mean, but okay we don't
know, but maybe we shouldn't presume that the same laws apply because
they're seen as not the primary actors. ואי אשמעינן דינים *v'ashmi-ein dinim*,
if it would have just told us law, that the civil law
applies to women, כי היכי דתהוי לה חיותא *ki-heichi di-tehavi lah chiyusa*,
in order that she should be able to make a living. Like
רש"י *Rashi* says, if she's not protected by law, laws don't govern
interactions with her, nobody's going to want to do business with a
woman because you never know what law's going to apply or nobody's
going to be she's not nobody's going to be protected. Okay, so
obviously you need it, even though it would be seen to be
unusual, but you need it because sometimes it happens. אבל כפרה kapara,
*aval kapara*, but when it comes to atonement, איש דבר מצוה *ish
de-bar mitzvah*, a man that has a big obligation in מצות *mitzvot*,
in yes he gets atonement. אבל אשה דלאו בת מצוה bat mitzvah
*aval isha d'lav bat mitzvah*, okay so much for saying that women
have בת מצות *bat mitzvahs*, a woman that is not the same
degree of obligated in מצות *mitzvot*, לא *lo*, maybe she shouldn't. Now
that's a very strange idea. First of all, right, now this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is a very challenging גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to our contemporary
sensibilities and it's going to get even more challenging. It's even going
to get more challenging in a minute, okay, but it's not just
saying okay women have a few מצות *mitzvot* that they do less
than men. It really is putting them on a fundamentally lower status.
Because they have fewer מצות *mitzvot* they're called not בר מצוה bar
mitzvah *bar mitzvah*, not בת מצוה *bat mitzvah* and therefore somehow not
deserving of atonement when they sin. Yeah whatever they do, do מצות
*mitzvot* do sins doesn't really matter so much or something like that.
Okay, it's obviously a disturbing הוה אמינא hava amina *hava amina*. And
then it goes yeah, works for you? Okay. ואי אשמעינן הני תרתי
*v'i-ashmi-ein hanei tarti*, even just said these two, הכא משום כפרה kapara,
והכא משום חיותא *hacha mishum kapara v'hacha mishum chiyusa*, in this case
it will apply to women so that they get an atonement, in
the other place so that they should be able to do business,
make a living. אבל וכי קטילא *aval v'chi ktila*, but when it
comes to being gored, now why should a woman not be able
to why should you not be liable when your ox gores a
woman? What would be the הוה אמינא hava amina *hava amina*? Now
here's where it becomes really challenging. איש דבר מצוה *ish de-bar mitzvah*,
a man that's obligated in מצות *mitzvot*, לשלומי כופר kofer, *l'shalemin kofer*,
I would have to pay... But אשה לא, but maybe if it
only killed a woman, and since she's not really so obligated in
מצוות, mitzvot, maybe I shouldn't really have to pay an atonement payment,
right? So that's obviously deeply disturbing. It seems to really devalue the
life of a woman because of this lesser obligation in מצוות. mitzvot.
Let's just finish. והא דקתני כופר משום דאיכא איבוד נשמה, Veha dekatni
kofer mishum de'ika ibbud neshama, just said you pay כופר, kofer that's
because דאיכא, de'ika, because there's a loss of life, so of course
you're going to pay for a man or a woman. אבל הני
תרתי דליכא איבוד נשמה, Aval hani tartei delika ibbud neshama, the other
two that there's no loss of life, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe
women wouldn't be included, צריכא, tzricha, so it tells me by default
women are included in all laws of the תורה, even those in
the male gender, unless explicitly identified otherwise. Yes. What was the statement
that she's not a בר מצוה bar mitzvah, בת מצוה in regards
to מצוות עשה? mitzvot aseh? Because the... Yes, I mean her exemption,
that's what's even more troubling, is that her exemption is from מצוות
עשה, mitzvot aseh, but somehow that should translate into a lesser value
of her life when she's gored, or translate into not bringing atonement
when she does a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So that's like what's
so, you know, like רב משה Rav Moshe has this classic תשובה.
tshuva. רב משה Rav Moshe was asked at the beginning of sort
of the Jewish feminist movement, which is he was asked by this
rabbi that he says these women in my שול shul are, you
know, are basically saying that the תורה, you know, doesn't, you know,
treats women as a lower status than men, you know, and how
do I respond to them? And רב משה Rav Moshe basically says,
look, even though women are exempt from some מצוות, mitzvot, חס ושלום
chas veshalom that that should mean that we ever see them on
a lower level of קדושה kedusha and on a lower status, and
he sort of, you know, presents this very nice picture. But you
read a גמרא Gemara like this and the גמרא Gemara, doesn't just
say it's a technical question of being obligated in few מצוות, mitzvot,
somehow that should mean that they, that when they do an עבירה
aveira it's less meaningful, when they get killed it's of less consequence.
The first the first דיוק diyuk is that they're חייב chayav in
all עונשים of the תורה, which is which is all לא תעשה,
lo ta'aseh, right? They're חייב מלקות chayav malkut for everything. Right. So
so so the גמרא's Gemara, already assuming that they're חייב. chayav. They
are חייב, chayav, but it's somehow saying, but but somehow even though
they're חייב, chayav, they're still considered not a fully בר מצוה, like
not a full, meaning the גמרא, Gemara it's sort of תוספות's Tosafot
question. When the גמרא, Gemara, what's the הוה אמינא hava amina if
you wouldn't say הישווה הכתוב אשה לאיש? hishva hakatuv isha le'ish? Would
it be that they don't get, you know, they're not they're not
covered by the לא תעשה lo ta'ases or they're covered by the
לא תעשה lo ta'ases they just don't bring קרבנות? So the גמרא's
Gemara a little bit unclear about that. But you are right in
one possibility of the גמרא, Gemara if you would have to read
that you wouldn't say הישווה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל עונשים, hishva hakatuv
isha le'ish lechol onashim, so it wouldn't just be the עשה, aseh,
it would even apply to most of the לא תעשה. lo ta'ases.
That's a possibility, yes. Wait, one thing that comes out of this,
I never fully realized, it sounds like the כופר kofer. is for
the benefit of the killer. Why? Right? Because it's כפרה. It's your
payment. That's a גמרא Gemara, discussion later in the גמרא Gemara is
כופר כפרה kofer kapara or כופר ממון. kofer mammon. But it's quite
clear why? Because if it's כפרה, right? Oh oh yeah, right? Right,
and so the payment, first of all, who does the payment go
to? So it goes to the heirs. Right, to the person who's
dead. But then in that context, like if it is if you
are paying because you need כפרה, then perhaps then you can kind
of understand this calculus of of, you know, מצוות mitzvot being done
in the world. Right. I know, I do understand where it's coming
from, but it's like disturbing, right? By the way, just to get
to that question of כופר כפרה ממון, kofer kapara mammon, whose value
do you pay for? The killed person or your life? Because it's
like your life deserves to be taken and instead of giving your
life you're giving the value of your life, right? So that's actually
a discussion in the גמרא, Gemara yes. The one thing I just
didn't understand the transition there, we said the והשווה איש או אשה,
vehishva ish o isha, we said איש השווה הכתוב איש לאשה ואשה
לאיש לכל עונשים שבתורה. ish hishva hakatuv ish le'isha ve'isha le'ish lechol
onashim shebatorah. But then we were talking about כופר. kofer. So why
would the הוה אמינא be then that oh if it killed a
woman maybe if I would have taken that it would go on
the פסוק pasuk it's talking about? השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת. hashor
yisakel vegam be'alav yummat. Nothing to do with the כופר. kofer, אם
כופר יושת עליו, im kofer yushat alav, isn't that the פסוק? pasuk
But maybe he would have said אם יומת? im yummat? In other
words, and that's going on השור יסקל. hashor yisakel. If you killed
a man then השור יסקל וגם בעליו. hashor yisakel vegam be'alav. If
you killed a woman, no. Okay, could be that too. I mean,
I don't know, תוספות Tosafot is not limiting it. If you look
at what תוספות Tosafot says, כלומר שחייבין עליה מיתה או כופר כמו
על איש דהכי אקרי קרא. kolomar shechayavin aleha mita o kofer kemo
al ish dehachi akri kra. So not just saying כופר, kofer the
כופר and all the other things that are related. I understand. But
we're not limited to that. By the way, תוספות Tosafot does say
that this idea of הישווה הכתוב hishva hakatuv is only when the
when talking about the fact that a פסוק is written in the
masculine. If the פסוק explicitly says איש, איש ish ish איש or
whatever, something like that, then we do presume it's talking about a
man unless you have something to include a woman. Meaning there's a
difference between being written in the masculine, you know, gender and just
and it saying if a man, right? So if it uses the
word איש... Well, that’s also a question, right? Yes. But we have
so many cases where women are equated to slaves and children. Right.
So maybe it’s not so surprising that creates this kind of an...
I understand that. So the מסקנא maskana of the סוגיא sugya is
nice, but the הוה אמינא is, does reflect certain presumptions of women’s
lower status, you know? All right. So now we go on. Oh,
by the way, I can’t pass this up without saying, spending a
second to read this תוספות Tosfot of אשר תשים לפניהם. asher tasim
lifneihem This is a תוספות Tosfot that appears throughout ש"ס Shas in
different contexts. Let’s take a look at it. Okay. Here is your
תוספות Tosfot איש לאיש. ish l’ish. תוספות Tosfot says: תימא הא לפניהם
לא איירי אלא בכשרים לדון, teima ha lifneihem lo ayri ela b’ksherim
ladun, because another דרשה drasha the גמרא Gemara. says אשר תשים לפניהם
lifneihem are not the people that are affected by the law, the
potential litigants, but the people that judge the law, the דיינים. dayanim.
So the גמרא gemara, actually reads לפניהם lifneihem to be in front
of the judges, okay, and says therefore you have to do it
in front of Jewish judges and not non-Jewish judges. Okay? הא לפניהם
לא איירי אלא בכשרים לדון דהכי דרשינן בפרק קמא לפניהם ולא לפני
הדיוטות. ha lifneihem lo ayri ela b’ksherim ladun d’hachi darshinan b’perek kama
lifneihem v’lo lifnei hedyotot. It has to be judges with סמיכה, smicha,
not commoners. So now we’ve got a problem. If לפניהם lifneihem refers
to those being judged and includes women, and לפניהם lifneihem also refers
to the judges, then that should include women as judges, if לפניהם
means men and women. But that’s not true! דאשה פסולה לדון, d’isha
psula ladun, but a woman can’t be a judge, דאמרינן בספרי כל
הכשר לדון כשר להעיד, d’amrinan b’Sifrei kol hachasher ladun kasher l’haid, that
if you can be a judge, you can be a witness, ואשה
פסולה לעדות, v’isha psula l’edut, a woman can’t be a witness, so
obviously she can’t be a judge, כדאמרינן בחובל פרק משנה האחת. k’damrinan
b’chovel perek mishnah ha’achat. ויש לומר דההיא דכל הכשר באיש איירי. v’yesh
lomar d’hahi d’chol hachasher b’ish ayri. No, when it says if you’re
a kosher judge, you’re a kosher witness, it means men who are
kosher judges are kosher witnesses. כל איש הכשר לדון כשר להעיד. kol
ish hachasher ladun kasher l’haid. Meaning, what תוספות Tosfot is saying is,
maybe a woman could be a judge. She can’t be a witness,
but she could be a judge. Okay, so actually this תוספות Tosfot
thinks that’s quite possible that a woman could be a כשר דיין,
kasher dayan, okay, and even though normally a presumption is a דיין
dayan is a כשר עד, kasher ed, that wouldn’t be true by
women. ומדכתיב והיא שופטה את ישראל דבורה, umidechtiv v’hi shofta et Yisrael
Devorah, okay, now how to read this, of course, to my wife’s...
anyway, says that she judged Israel, אין להביא ראיה דאשה כשירה לדון.
ein l’havi reaya d’isha kshira ladun. Now, of course, the real reason
is אין להביא ראיה ein l’havi reaya is because it’s talking about
political leadership and not because about being a, you know, sort of
a, you know, justice of the court. But anyway, דשמא היו מקבלים
אותה עליהם מפני שכינה. d’shema hayu mekabelim ota aleihem mipnei Shchina.
Well, okay, she was a prophet, so okay, maybe that made it
an exception and they were willing to
accept her as a judge.
So it’s sort of like, you know, because you can accept פסול
pasul people to be your judges, a
type of arbitration, binding arbitration, but that doesn’t really mean that women...
anyway, תוספות Tosfot leaves it as an open question whether a woman
could be a כשר דיין, kasher dayan, which is quite fascinating. All
right, moving on in the גמרא. gemara Yes, so who says a
woman can’t have סמיכה? smicha? But that would be... that’s true. That’s
another point, good point. There you go, according to that possibility she’s
also getting the
סמיכה smicha and she’s in the פרשה parsha
of אלהים, Elohim, it’s not just כשר לדון. kasher ladun. All right.
הניזק והמזיק בתשלומין. hanizak v’hamazik b’tashlumin. Both the damaged and the damager
participate in the payment. איתמר. itmar. So now we’re going to see
what this bases onto. Now we get to a very central question
about קרן keren that we’ve been referring to all along. פלגא נזקא,
palga nizka, half damages by קרן. keren. רב פפא אמר ממונא רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמר קנסא. Rav Papa amar mamona, Rav Huna
brei d’Rav Yehoshua amar knasa. Rav Papa says it’s compensation and Rav
Huna says, no, it’s a fine. You really should be exempt and
anything you’re paying is more than you should be paying. רב פפא
אמר ממונא קסבר סתם שוורים לאו בחזקת שימור קיימי, Rav Papa amar
mamona kasvar stam shvarim lav b’chezkat shimur kaimi, that most oxen as
a rule are not to be presumed to be watched, self-protected, meaning
even though it’s never gored before, you can’t say that it doesn’t
need to be watched. Okay? And even a normal ox that has
never gored still needs to be... you need to keep your eye
on it. And if you don’t keep your eye on it and
it goes and gores, there’s an element of negligence there. Okay? ובדין
הוא דבעי לשלומי כולי. u’vadin hu d’baei l’shlumei kulei. So therefore, since
there is an element of negligence, you should be paying full. ורחמנא
הוא דחס עליה, v’Rachmana hu d’chas aleih, but the Torah has a
little רחמנות rachmanut on you. דאכתי לאו ייעד, d’achti lav yaad, because
it has not been through the מועד muad process, it hasn’t done
it three times, which means you’re right at the edge. You know,
technically there was negligence, but it was still pretty unlikely that it
would happen, but it was just likely enough that you should have
been watching. So there’s a small degree of negligence, but because it’s
right at the edge, the Torah is going to go easy on
you and make you only have to pay half. Okay? But it’s
ממון. mamon. You really were negligent, you are really paying for damages
that you are to blame for. Okay? That’s his opinion. רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע אמר קנסא. Rav Huna brei d’Rav Yehoshua amar knasa.
No, it’s a fine. קסבר סתם שוורים בחזקת שימור קיימי. kasvar stam
shvarim b’chezkat shimur kaimi. A normal ox you can presume will be
watched. protected, will from going out and damaging, does not require you
to keep your eye on it, and therefore you're not negligent. ובדינו
דלא לשלם כלל, u'bedinu d'lo leshalem klal, you really shouldn't have to
pay at all. ורחמנא הוא דקנסיה, v'rachamana hu d'kansei, the Torah fined
you, כי היכי דלינטריה לתוריה, ki heichi d'lintrei l'torei, to get you
to be more careful watching your oxen, maybe certainly more careful if
you did if it already damaged, but maybe in general get everybody
to up their level of care. The fact that you know that
you're going to have to pay half, even though you could say,
"Look, you know, technically I wasn't negligent." It's fine you weren't negligent,
but we're going to tell you you have to pay half anyway
and that's going to get everybody to do a higher level of
care than the strict law would have demanded, and that would prevent
a certain amount of damage from occurring. So the easiest way to
see it is that they're both agreeing that this is right on
the line. Something that you only pay half, clearly it's in some
gray zone. One just says it's a little bit above the line
and the Torah's going easy on you, and the other says it's
a little bit below the line and the Torah's going a little
bit harder on you. Yes? I'm I get the paternalism, but I'm
bothered by this second use of רחמנא. Why isn't it בית דין
beit din דקנסיה? d'kansei? Because it's in the Torah. The Torah says
you pay half. We're trying to understand what's behind the Torah's judgment
that you pay ruling that you pay half. It's really fascinating. בית
דין beit din imposes the קנס, knas, but the Torah is the
one that creates the law. Right. But in other words, for the
can can the can a בית דין beit din impose a קנס
knas in general if it's not backed up by a Yes.
I mean, חז"ל chazal can make their own קנסות. knasot. Okay, but
when we're saying
קנס, knas, but we can identify things in the Torah. שלושים של
עבד, shloshim shel eved, כפל. kefel. Right. It's actually a different level
of קנס knas here in a way. Yeah, I mean, it's a
תורה קנס. knas. I mean, yes, בית דין, beit din, חז"ל chazal
can make up their own קנסות knasot as well, but that's not
what we're talking about. Yes? I was actually going to use different
words but I was like, forget about whether the ox should or
shouldn't be watched, you should be paying full קנס knas it caused
damage. Forget about, forget about. Oh, so you want to say a
question of strict liability? So that's a good question. What Michael is
saying is, and I'll just mention and go on, it's a question
we've had from day one of בבא קמא, bava kamma, which is,
do you fundamentally start by an idea of strict liability, and the
only reason that you're פטור pattur is because you claim to be
an אונס? oness? Or do you start from an idea, no, no,
no, I'm only חייב chayav if I was negligent and my negligence
led to it? So the obvious נפקא מינא nafka mina is the
cases that are a little bit gray. If you start by strict
liability, I'm sorry buddy, you can't claim אונס. oness. If whereas if
you start from a position of negligence, you know, say, well, since
you clear you weren't clearly negligent, you're exempt. So that's a very
good point. A case that's like this, that's right at the border,
you could say if I start from strict liability, I'm going to
have to pay because I can't claim that it was I was
אונס. oness. If I start from a question of that I'm exempt
until you can prove negligence, I shouldn't have to pay. So that's
a that is a very nice way of saying it. I don't
think that that's necessarily in the words of the גמרא, gemara but
I but I agree with you that that is a core question
to be asked throughout בבא קמא. bava kamma. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תנן: tenan: הניזק והמזיק בתשלומין. hanizak vehamazik
betashlumin. Now the משנה mishna says here that the ניזק nizak and
the מזיק mazik both participate in paying for the damage. So we
assume that means when you pay half, everybody loses half. You I
lose half of my cow that I don't get compensated for, and
you pay me for half of my cow. So we both participated
in paying for the damage. All right, one minute, we'll get to
that. Okay. So בשלמא למאן דאמר פלגא ניזקא ממונא, bishlama leman d'amar
palga nizka mamona, if if it's real compensation, so you should be
paying me full, but instead of you paying me full, I'm essentially
paying for half of my own loss. היינו דשייך ניזק והמזיק בתשלומין.
hainu d'shaich nizak vehamazik betashlumin. So that's why I'm participating in the
payment, because I'm not getting fully paid, so I essentially am paying
for half of my own loss. אלא למאן דאמר פלגא ניזקא קנסא,
ella leman d'amar palga nizka knasa, but if you really don't owe
me anything, so then everything I get is a windfall because technically
you should be fully exempt. השתא דלאו דידיה שקיל, hashta d'lav didei
shakil, if I'm getting half of something that I don't deserve because
you really aren't negligent, בתשלומין איתא, betashlumin ita, what does it mean
that I am paying for my own loss? Now, I still am
out my cow, okay, but the phrase so clearly at the end
of the day I did lose half of the value of something
I own due to no fault of my own, okay, but nevertheless
it's not like I paid for the תשלומין tashlumin because there was
no תשלומין tashlumin to be paid, it was all stuff I didn't
deserve. Okay. Now, so the גמרא Gemara says, לא נצרכא אלא לפחת
נבילה. lo nitzrecha ella lephachas neveila. Fine, according to that read that
it's קנס, knas, the idea that I participate in payment is coming
to be this other הלכה halacha that we taught: that I'm left
with the carcass and any depreciation of the carcass I have to
suffer. So even though your ox gored mine and you should be
paying me, if the carcass continues to deteriorate, nevertheless I participate in
the payment because I suffer the loss of the value of the
carcass. פחת נבילה התנא ליה רישא. phachas neveila hatana lei reisha. Wait
a minute, we taught that in an earlier משנה. mishna. תשלומי נזק
מלמד שהבעלים מטפלין בנבילה, tashlumei nezek melamed shehabalim metaplin beneveila, that was
a phrase of תשלומי נזק, tashlumei nezek, which we said earlier the
phrase of that משנה mishna meant that I have to suffer the
loss of the depreciation of the carcass. חדא בתם וחדא במועד. chada
b'tam vechada b'muad. One is talking about when my ox was gored
by a תם tam and one when it was gored by a
מועד, muad, וצריכא, utzricha, you need to tell me in both cases.
I own the carcass and suffer the loss. דאי אשמעינן תם Tam
*D'iy ashmi'inan tam*, מפני שאכתי לא הועד *mip'nei she'akati lo yuad*, so
of course we're going to go easier on the מזיק *mazik* because
his ox hasn't been warned. So I, the ניזק *nizak*, will have
to suffer the loss of the depreciation of the carcass. אבל מועד
Muad. *Aval muad*, but when the ox is gored multiple times, אימא
לא *eima lo*, we won't go so easy on the מזיק *mazik*.
Maybe the מזיק *mazik* has to suffer the loss? ואי אשמעינן מועד
Muad. *Ve'iy ashmi'inan muad*, if it told me by מועד *muad* I
suffer the loss, משום דקמשלם כוליה *mishum d'kameshalem kulei*, because the מזיק
*mazik* is paying full, so at least we could do if the
מזיק *mazik* is paying full is let me suffer the loss. אבל
תם Tam *Aval tam*, but by the first three times, אימא לא
*eima lo*, since he's only paying half, let him suffer the loss.
צריכא *Tzricha*, so it has to tell me whether תם Tam, *tam*
or מועד *muad*, I suffer the loss. Okay, so that's two ways
of reading ניזק ומזיק בתשלומין *nizak u'mazik betashlumin*. It's obviously a more
elegant read to say that when half is paid, it's like they're
both losing out half. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says conceptually even
though it's always true they're both losing out half, conceptually what that
means is it fits the idea of פלגא ניזקא ממונא *palga nizka
mamona*, that he owes me the full amount and I essentially am
paying for half of what's owed to me. All right, now we're
going to try to deal with this question of whether פלגא ניזקא
ממונא או קנסא *palga nizka mamona o knasa*. תא שמע Ta Shema,
*Ta shema*, come in here. מה בין תם למועד שבתם משלם Meshalem?
חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek מגופו ומועד משלם נזק שלם מן העלייה *Ma
bein tam lemuad shebetam meshalem chatzi nezek migufo u'muad meshalem nezek shalem
min ha'aliya*? What's the difference between תם *tam* and מועד *muad*? תם
*Tam* pays half from the body of the animal, and a מועד
*muad* pays full from the עלייה *aliya*, from like the best property
or whatever, okay, or from the attic, whatever. Meaning it does not
pay out of the body of the animal. ואי איתא *Ve'iy ita*,
if it was also this הלכה *halacha* that half damages is a
קנס Knas, *knas*, then we should point out other differences between half
and full. ליתני נמי התם אינו משלם על פי עצמו *Litni nami
hatam eino meshalem al pi atzmo*. תם *Tam*, you don't pay by
self-admission because it's a קנס Knas. *knas*. One of the consequences of
being a קנס Knas. *knas* like we said is you don't pay
by self-admission. מועד משלם על פי עצמו *Muad meshalem al pi atzmo*,
and מועד *muad* does. So since it did not give the case
of self-admission as a difference, it seems like it's ממונא *mamona*, that
it's not really fundamentally a different type of payment. אמר תנא ושייר
*Amar tana v'shayer*. Yes fine, it should have said that, but it's
an incomplete list. מאי שייר דהאי שייר *Mai shayer d'hai shayer*? What
else is different if you מודה *modeh* in it? Yes, if you
admit that my ox gored, then yes the קנס Knas. *knas* you
don't have to pay. מאי שייר *Mai shayer*? What else was left
off the list? שייר חצי כופר *Shayer chatzi kofer*. It left off
the list כופר *kofer*. By a מועד *muad* you pay full and
by a תם *tam* you don't pay חצי כופר *chatzi kofer*, you
pay nothing. ולא תני *Ve'lo tani*. Meaning that you don't pay חצי
כופר *chatzi kofer*. So another difference between תם *tam*
and מועד *muad* is
that מועד *muad* is full and תם *tam* is half. מועד *Muad*
pays כופר *kofer* and תם *tam* pays no כופר *kofer*. Okay. אי
משום חצי כופר לא שייר *Ei mishum chatzi kofer lo shayer*, but
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it can't prove that that means that
something was left off the list because there is somebody that says
a חצי כופר *chatzi kofer* actually you do pay. הא מני רבי
יוסי הגלילי היא דאמר תם משלם חצי כופר *Ha mani Rabbi Yosei
HaGlili hi d'amar tam meshalem chatzi kofer*. Fine, so there is an
opinion that you do pay חצי כופר *chatzi kofer*. It's not clearly
left off the list. But anyway, this fact that it did not
identify קנס Knas. *knas* as a basis of difference of תם *tam*
and מועד *muad* seems to be a good indication that it's ממונא
*mamona*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says maybe it's an incomplete list.
תא שמע *Ta shema*, let's try to prove it again. המית שורי
את פלוני או שורו של פלוני *Heimit shori et ploni o shoro
shel ploni*. Here's a case of admitting. I admit that my ox
gored somebody. Okay, gored, or it, and then it would be paying
כופר *kofer*. Or it gored somebody's ox. הרי זה משלם על פי
עצמו *Harei zeh meshalem al pi atzmo*. I have to pay based
on my own admission. So מאי לאו Mai Lav, בתם *mai lav
betam*? Presumably we didn't say only by a מועד *muad*, presumably we're
talking even about a תם *tam* and I would pay by my
own admission that my ox gored. So you see that it's ממונא
*mamona*, it's not קנס Knas? *knas*. לא במועד *Lo bemuad*. No, maybe
we're talking about a מועד *muad* and that's why you're paying on
your own admission. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute. אבל תם
מאי *Aval tam mai*? What would you say therefore if that's talking
about a מועד *muad* and you want to say that תם *tam*
is a קנס Knas? *knas*? הכא נמי דלא משלם על פי עצמו
*Hacha nami d'lo meshalem al pi atzmo*? Would you say if it
was a case of a תם *tam* I wouldn't pay? אי הכי
Ee Hachi, אדתני סיפא *Ei hachi adatani seifa*? The end of that
ברייתא Braita, *braita* says המית שורי את עבדו של פלוני אין In,
משלם על פי עצמו *Heimit shori et avdo shel ploni ein meshalem
al pi atzmo*. If I admit not to כופר *kofer* and not
to נזק *nezek* but I admit that it gored a slave. What
do you pay by a slave? You pay thirty שקל *shekel*. That's
a קנס Knas. *knas*. So it says if I admit that it
gored a slave, then I don't pay on my own admission. That's
a קנס Knas. *knas*. So what the point of this text is
doing is it's contrasting when I admit to תשלומין *tashlumin* I pay
based on my own admission, when I admit to a קנס Knas.
*knas* I don't. So it says why are we contrasting it talking
about goring an ox versus goring a slave? Why don't we just
contrast it between admitting to a case of a מועד *muad* versus
admitting to a case of a תם *tam*? לפלוג וליתני בדידיה *Liflog
u'litni bididiah*. במה דברים אמורים *Bemei devarim amurim*?
When does my own admission obligate me? במועד *Bemuad*. אבל בתם *Aval
betam*, let it tell me that if it gored an ox and
it was a תם *tam*, אין משלם על פי עצמו *ein meshalem
al pi atzmo*. I wouldn't, that that's a קנס Knas. *knas*. So
again, the fact that the only קנס Knas. *knas* it can find
is
the case of a slave seems to be saying that a case
of a תם *tam* goring is not a קנס Knas. *knas*.
No, כולי במועד קאיירי, we want to
talk about contrasting cases of מועד. We're not dealing with the תם
scenario. אי הכי נמי, Ee Hachi Nami, תם is also a קנס,
Knas? but we're not talking about תם, we're talking about מועד. All
right, let's try to read one more case. תא שמע, זה הכלל
כל המשלם יותר על מה שהזיק אינו משלם על פי עצמו. Ze
Haklal Kol HaMeshalem Yoter Al Mah SheHizik Eino Meshalem Al Pi Atzmo.
Here's a this is a really important ברייתא, Braita here's a way
to know if something is ממון Mamon or קנס. Knas, How do
you know? If you're paying more than the damages, that's קנס. Knas.
Okay? כל המשלם יותר, Kol HaMeshalem Yoter, like כפל, Kefel, כל המשלם
יותר על מה שהזיק אינו משלם על פי עצמו. Kol HaMeshalem Yoter
Al Mah SheHizik Eino Meshalem Al Pi Atzmo. If it's more than,
you don't pay by your admission, that's קנס. Knas, So לישני, Lishnei,
so wait a minute, did I skip a line? מאי לאו, הפחות
ממה שהזיק, HaPachot MiMah SheHizik, משלם? That is ממון. Mamon. It's not
full ממון, Mamon, but it's ממון Mamon if you pay less. And
so that seems to be another proof that it's ממון. Mamon. וואו,
Woah, no, הא קמשמע לן, Ha Kamashma Lan, no, if you pay
exactly the same amount, that's ממון. Mamon. Okay? But more or less
is קנס. Knas. So the גמרא says one minute. אבל פחות מאי?
Aval Pachot Mai? So you would tell me less than the full
amount, הכי נמי דלא משלם? Hachi Nami DeLo Meshalem? You would tell
me that you don't pay on your own admission? That whether more
or less, it's קנס? אי הכי, if that's true, אדקתני, Ad'tani, then
it gave me the wrong rule. Why did it tell me the
rule was זה הכלל כל המשלם יותר על מה שהזיק אינו משלם
על פי עצמו? Ze Haklal Kol HaMeshalem Yoter Al Mah SheHizik Eino
Meshalem Al Pi Atzmo? Why didn't it say the rule was if
you pay more, you don't pay by your own admission, that more
than the amount of damages is קנס? The more precise rule would
have been what? What's the more precise rule? Any time you don't
pay the exact amount is קנס. לישני זה הכלל כל שאינו משלם
כמה שהזיק. Lishnei Ze Haklal Kol She'eino Meshalem K'mah SheHizik. Tell me
if you're not paying the exact amount, דמשמע פחות ומשמע יותר, Demashma
Pachot Umashma Yoter, which would tell me more or less than the
exact amount is קנס. תיובתא, Tiyuvta, you're right, that's a complete contradiction.
It shows from that ברייתא Braita. that חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek is
ממון, Mamon, that if you're not paying more, it's ממון Mamon and
not קנס. And then the גמרא does its great thing, והלכתא, V'hilcheta,
now that we've proven that חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek is ממון, Mamon,
פלגא ניזקא קנסא, Palga Nizka Knasa, we rule that חצי נזק Chatzi
Nezek is קנס. So the גמרא says תיובתא והלכתא? Tiyuvta V'hilcheta? You
just showed me a contradiction
and now you're ruling that way? So the גמרא says אין, yes.
טעמא מאי הוי תיובתא? Ta'ama Mai Havei Tiyuvta? Why did we think
it was such a contradiction? Because משום דלא קתני כמה שהזיק. Mishum
Delo Katani K'mah SheHizik. It didn't say that any time you don't
pay exact damage, it's קנס. And because it didn't say that, it
sounded like less would be ממון. Mamon. No, לא פסיקא ליה, Lo
Psika Lei, that's not always true. There are times when you pay
less than full and it's ממון. Mamon. What's a time you pay
less than full and it's ממון? Mamon? Not by a goring ox,
כיון דאיכא חצי נזק צרורות. Keivan De'ika Chatzi Nezek Tzerorot. Remember our
half damages of צרורות, Tzerorot, of the pebbles that get kicked? So
that is a case where you were fully negligent, right? There was
a reason there was not lack of negligence, it was just indirect.
It was the animal's כח Koach and not the direct body of
the animal. So there there's a half payment, but it actually is
ממון. Mamon. Okay? דהלכתא גמירי לה דממונא הוא, Dehilcheta Gmiri Lah DeMamona
Hu, we have a tradition that that is ממון. Mamon. משום הכי
לא קתני, Mishum Hachi Lo Katani, therefore it didn't say. So what
are we saying? When you pay more, כפל, Kefel, ארבעה וחמישה, Arba'ah
V'chamishah, it's always קנס. When you pay less, sometimes it's ממון. Mamon.
Sometimes you really are obligated but we're letting you off easy. What
would be an example of that? חצי נזק צרורות Chatzi Nezek Tzerorot
where you had full negligence but because it was indirect, it was
the pebbles or whatever, you're only going to pay half. How about
חצי נזק קנס? Chatzi Nezek Knas? Is that ממון, Mamon, is that
קנס? That's not clear from that ברייתא. Braita What's clear from that
ברייתא Braita, is sometimes when you pay less, it's ממון. Mamon. But
whether חצי נזק of a goring ox is ממון Mamon or קנס,
that's not clear from that ברייתא, and the גמרא actually rules that
we're going to rule that it's קנס. Even though all the evidence
seemed to be ממון, Mamon, we managed to get out of all
the evidence and we left it as an open possibility and we're
going to actually rule that it's קנס, and we are going to
pick up tomorrow which is discussing the implications of that ruling that
חצי נזק קרן Chatzi Nezek Keren is קנס. So we'll pick up
with that tomorrow.